<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter of November the 16th from an eminent officer in the army at Edenburgh to a friend at London, declaring the true number of the horse and foot now under General Monck, and their unanimons [sic] resolution to adventure all for the support of magistracie and ministrie, the rights of the people, and priviledges of Parliament : all which are now endeavoured to be subverted by that part of the Army under Colonel Lambert and others about London.</title>
            <author>A. B., Eminent officer in the army at Edenburgh.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48121</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1573C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2965</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12890094</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12890094</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95090</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48121)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95090)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 718:36)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter of November the 16th from an eminent officer in the army at Edenburgh to a friend at London, declaring the true number of the horse and foot now under General Monck, and their unanimons [sic] resolution to adventure all for the support of magistracie and ministrie, the rights of the people, and priviledges of Parliament : all which are now endeavoured to be subverted by that part of the Army under Colonel Lambert and others about London.</title>
                  <author>A. B., Eminent officer in the army at Edenburgh.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], 3-8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At end: "I was commanded by my L. Monck to write to you, and to give you this brief account of our affairs ... A.B."</note>
                  <note>In the Harvard copy these initials have been filled out in ms. to Abraam Bell.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Albemarle, George Monck, --  Duke of, 1608-1670.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History, Military --  1603-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95090:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 65 -->
            <p>A LETTER Of <hi>November</hi> the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi>:</p>
            <p>From an eminent Officer in the Army at <hi>Edenburgh</hi> to a friend at <hi>London,</hi> declaring the true num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the horſe and foot now under General <hi>Monck,</hi> and their unanimons Reſolution to adventure all for the ſupport of Magiſtracie and Miniſtrie, the Rights of the People, and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of Parliament; all which are now endeavoured to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted by that part of the Army under Colonel <hi>Lambert</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers about <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:95090:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 66 -->
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>MY Lord General <hi>Monck</hi> not knowing if his Letter to your Brother, came ſafe to him, commanded me to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his ſervice to you. We are here, the LORD be praiſed, all of a piece, reſolv'd to venture all for the eſtabliſhment of the Ordinances of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracie and Miniſtrie: ſome time ſince his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſent to acquaint ſuch of the horſe that were not free to act, That they ſhould have liberty to goe whither they would, and about 55. of <hi>Twi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleton</hi>'s Regiment, moſt of Capt. <hi>Davies</hi> Troop, and 24. of his own Regiment of horſe, went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. We ſhall march ſomewhat more then ſix thouſand good Foot, and two thouſand horſe, and leave our Garriſons well enough ſupplied. Yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the Nobility and Gentry of the <hi>Scottish</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion met at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> and have engaged to live peaceably upon our marchaway, they have offered large aſſiſtance of men, but my Lord Generall meddles not with any of them, four of the County
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95090:3"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 67 -->troops of <hi>Northumberland</hi> are come in to us, and three more had come but they were ſuppreſs'd by contrary orders from <hi>Newcaſtle:</hi> But we doubt not, by that time we get a few daies into <hi>England,</hi> recruits both from the Army and Countrey will come in unto us, for we have certain intelligence that their men are much divided, and many of the moſt pious Officers lay down their Commiſſions, and few but Anabaptiſts and thoſe that are profeſt enemies to Miniſtrie engage againſt us, except the nine whoſe Commiſsions were taken away by the Parliament, and ſome of them are of that judgement alſo. We hear at <hi>London</hi> they ſpeak ſtrangely of us for ſecuring Colonel <hi>Cobbet</hi> and ſome other ſeditious Officers that went about to divide us here, whom they call ſober godly men. As for <hi>Cobbet,</hi> I know not how my Lord could doe otherwiſe, he being one that came to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand his Regiment after the Parliament had made his Commiſsion void, and being one of the moſt active in their interruption; and likewiſe his Lordſhip had certain intelligence that he came to <hi>Scotland</hi> to ſecure his perſon if he could not draw him to join with thoſe at <hi>London</hi> in their wicked practiſes: but as for the other Officers, after they were at firſt ſecured to prevent their diſturbance of the peace of this Army, as many of them as were free to own the Parliaments Authority from whence they received their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95090:3"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 67 -->Commiſsions, were admitted to their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and the reſt have their pay continued to them: but truly, as for their ſobriety, I think few in <hi>Bedlam</hi> were leſſe wild in all honeſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and the beſt marks of Godlineſſe we could obſerve in them, were hatred, violence, emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſtrife, ſedition, hereſies, envyings, revile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and ſuch like: and notwithſtanding all their pretences for the Good Old Cauſe, and the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intereſt, their whole endeavour hath been to ingroſſe all power to themſelves: and moſt of the Officers in <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> of late put in, were all of that judgement; and all that were for Magiſtracie and Miniſtrie, reviled and call'd Prieſt-ridden, and the like; and I am confident, not any but of theſe ſort will oppoſe us: Major General <hi>Morgan</hi> came in to us the 6th inſtant, he brought a letter from my Lord <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> to mediate for peace, but hearing my Lord General and our Officers (upon an earneſt deſire of my Lord <hi>Fleetwood</hi>) had ſent up three of our number, Commiſsioners to endeavour to beget a good underſtanding betwixt us &amp; our brethren; he wrote a letter to my Lord <hi>Lambert</hi> by Colonel <hi>Talbot,</hi> wherein he told him, if the Treaty ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded not, he deſired to be excuſed if he acted in his ſtation where his command lay, and he is at preſent with his Regiment, putting it into good order, it being lately chang'd from Dragoons to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95090:4"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 68 -->be Horſe; ſince his coming to us Lieut. Colonel <hi>Ledger</hi> a <hi>Yorkshire</hi> Gentleman that was Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Col. of <hi>Flanders</hi> Regiments now at <hi>York,</hi> hath laid down his Commiſsion, declaring, he cannot with conſcience act againſt us, &amp; we have a rumor that Col. <hi>Samuel Clark</hi> his Col. hath done the like, and many more will do ſo or better, of whoſe names it is not ſafe to write at this time. The Regiments that march'd from <hi>London</hi> were very unruly in their march, <hi>Duckenfield</hi>'s men would not indure him at the head of them, and cried out they would have a Parliament, and <hi>Salmons</hi> men were very rude upon the Countrey in free Quarter and violencies. My Lord Gen. has been ſo good an husband for us, that we are all paid, and have enough for <hi>December</hi> and <hi>Ianuary;</hi> and we ſhall march with much chearfulneſſe. All true <hi>English</hi> men, that think no hazard too much for the Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of Magiſtracy and Miniſtry, the liberties of the people, and priviledges of Parliament. I preſume by this time our Commiſsioners know what to truſt to, their time is almoſt expired, and if they cannot make a good accommodation we ſhould be glad to ſee them here, that we may doe our duties in this our generation to ſave the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from confuſion in civil and ſpiritual liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which vvere never ſo near ſubverſion as novv; Indeed if they at <hi>London</hi> had ever yet ſtuck to any declaration they ever emitted, one might
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95090:5"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 68 -->expect ſomething from them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but at a Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee of Officers at Whitehall, about the 24th of Octob. (of which we have here certain notice from and of them;) They being in debate about Tythes and Miniſters maintenance, one of them (a Colonel) ſaid he was both againſt Miniſters &amp; their maintenance alſo, but yet the time was not come to take them away, and therefore they ſhould declare at large, are theſe the Co<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſels of Saints? Truly I muſt tell you with grief of heart, we are certainly inform'd here, That the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers at <hi>Wallingford</hi> Houſe never meet in a day of Prayer, but the hearts of ſober Godly people are afflicted at it, finding all thoſe devotions but the Forerunners to ſome grievous miſchiefs in perpetration. How can my Lord <hi>Fleetwood</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit himſelf of the private engagement he made in the Parliament the day before he acted in their interruption, and how can <hi>Sydenham</hi> be freed from the publick Engagement and Profeſsion he made, and with what conſcience can <hi>Salway</hi> Act to model Governments, that was ſo ſevere againſt all things done in theſe yeares from the firſt interruption in 53. Upon the 5. of this moneth Captain <hi>Dean</hi> the Treaſurer brought us a letter from the Officers at <hi>Whitehal,</hi> which was ſent as an anſwer to ours from <hi>Linlithgowe</hi> dated the 22. of <hi>October,</hi> &amp; diſperſ'd many copies of it to ſeduce the Souldiers, ſo that aſſoon as our Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95090:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 69 -->had framed an Anſwer to it, my Lord Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral cauſed both their Letter and our Anſwer to be Printed, and I have ſent them to you here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed, and I deſire you would get them Printed if you can, for I think they are well worth publick view.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute> 
                     <signed>Your very humble ſervant.</signed>
                     <dateline>Edinburgh, <date>
                           <hi>this</hi> 16. <hi>of Novemb.</hi> 1659.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>I was commanded by my <hi>L. Monck</hi> to write to you, and to give you this brief Account of our Affairs, I hope you will pardon this boldneſſe of</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>Sir,</salute> 
                        <signed>your very humble ſervant,
<hi>A. B.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
